<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<spec name="filament">

  <description>
    This specification defines the filament command-line tool: the tool packaging, the marker format, the state file structure, the drift model, the public API, the output format, the self-hosting test, the versioning, and the parser rules. Anything not covered by these clauses is unspecified. The key words MUST, MUST NOT, SHOULD, SHOULD NOT, and MAY in this specification are to be interpreted as described in [RFC2119] and [RFC8174]. [RFC2119] Bradner, S., "Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels," March 1997. [RFC8174] Leiba, B., "Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC 2119 Keywords," May 2017.
  </description>

  <definitions>
    <term text="id">The dotted-path identifier of an element in a spec, given in its attribute.</term>
    <term text="hash_output">The byte sequence that the digest function produces.</term>
    <term text="term">An element in a definitions block, identified by an attribute. An element of this kind has prose content and is cited by clauses and other terms.</term>
    <term text="clause">An element, identified by a path, that has prose content and no sub-elements. An element of this kind is a leaf in the spec tree.</term>
    <term text="section">An element, identified by a path, that has a human-readable name and one or more sub-elements. An element of this kind groups clauses and other sections under a common name.</term>
    <term text="child_id">The id of a clause or section that is a child of a section; it is formed by appending .{segment} to the parent's id, where {segment} matches [a-z0-9_]+.</term>
    <term text="reference">A maximal run of [a-z0-9_.]+ in a clause's or term's prose content that, after stripping any trailing characters not in [a-z0-9_], exactly matches the id of a defined clause, section, or term in the same spec.</term>
    <term text="hash_input">The byte sequence that the digest function consumes.</term>
    <term text="separator">The single newline byte (0x0A) used to join segments of the hash_input.</term>
    <term text="text">The prose content of a clause or term.</term>
    <term text="label">The human-readable name of a section, given in its attribute.</term>
    <term text="marker">A line in a text file that contains the substring #F followed by whitespace and the literal id:. The line is matched regardless of any comment prefix that precedes it.</term>
    <term text="marker_id">An 8-character identifier for a marker site, composed of lowercase letters (a-z) and digits (0-9), generated using a cryptographically secure random source.</term>
    <term text="well_formed_marker">A marker whose marker_id is exactly 8 characters of [a-z0-9], followed by one or more whitespace-separated clause_ids that are defined ids in the spec.</term>
    <term text="malformed_marker">A marker that is not a well_formed_marker.</term>
    <term text="content_window">The N lines immediately after a marker line in a text file. N defaults to 10 and is configurable.</term>
    <term text="content_hash">SHA-256 of the normalized content_window of a marker, hex-encoded as 64 lowercase hex characters.</term>
    <term text="reviewed_spec_hash">The hex string stored per marker-clause pair in the state file, representing the clause digest at the time the marker was last reviewed against that clause.</term>
    <term text="spec_drift">A marker whose reviewed_spec_hash does not match the current clause digest for a clause it references. This condition means the clause changed since the marker was last reviewed.</term>
    <term text="site_drift">A marker whose content_hash does not match the stored content digest for that marker in the state file. This condition means the content near the marker changed since the marker was last stored.</term>
    <term text="missing">A clause in the spec that has no well_formed_marker in any scanned file. Only clauses are subject to this condition; sections and terms are structural or vocabulary and are never reported.</term>
    <term text="orphan">A well_formed_marker that references a clause id not in the spec.</term>
    <term text="duplicate_marker">A well_formed_marker whose marker_id appears in more than one scanned file. Each marker_id MUST be unique across all scanned files.</term>
    <term text="filament_file">The .filament file in the project root that stores clause digests, content digests, and reviewed digests. It is the source of truth for change detection.</term>
    <term text="workspace">The directory tree tracked by filament, containing the .filament file and the text files with markers.</term>
  </definitions>

  <section id="tool" label="Tool">
    <clause id="tool.name">The tool is named filament.</clause>
    <clause id="tool.location">The tool lives at /filament in the project root.</clause>
    <clause id="tool.language">The tool MUST be implemented in Go. The tool MUST NOT provide bindings in any other language.</clause>
    <clause id="tool.design">The tool MUST NOT depend on any package outside the Go standard library, MUST NOT cite the project in its import path, and MUST NOT expose project-specific identifiers in its public API.</clause>
    <clause id="tool.binary">The compiled binary MUST be named filament.</clause>
  </section>

  <section id="path_format" label="Path format">
    <clause id="path_format.structure">A path is a dot-separated string of one or more segments.</clause>
    <clause id="path_format.charset">Each segment matches the regular expression [a-z0-9_]+.</clause>
    <clause id="path_format.depth">The path has unbounded depth; practical limits are imposed by the host environment.</clause>
  </section>

  <section id="hash" label="Hash format">
    <clause id="hash.algorithm">The hash is SHA-256 of the clause's hash_input, hex-encoded.</clause>
    <section id="hash.input" label="Hash input">
      <clause id="hash.input.content">The content of a clause or term is the text. The content of a section is the value of the section's label attribute.</clause>
      <clause id="hash.input.references">The references are the hash_outputs of every clause, section, or term cited by this clause or term. Sections have no references because they have no text content.</clause>
      <clause id="hash.input.references_order">The references appear in the order their reference tokens first appear in the clause's or term's text, left to right; tokens with the same first-occurrence position are ordered by lexical comparison of the cited id.</clause>
      <clause id="hash.input.whitespace">Leading and trailing whitespace of the content are trimmed before it is joined.</clause>
      <clause id="hash.input.separator">A single separator byte is placed between the content and the first reference, and between each pair of consecutive references.</clause>
    </section>
    <section id="hash.output" label="Hash output">
      <clause id="hash.output.format">A hash_output is a lowercase hex string of 64 characters, with no prefix.</clause>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="marker_format" label="Marker format">
    <clause id="marker_format.syntax">A well_formed_marker is a line containing the following elements in order: the substring #F, whitespace, the literal id:, a marker_id, whitespace, and one or more clause_ids separated by whitespace. The line MAY contain the literal -- followed by whitespace-separated key=value pairs after the clause_ids.</clause>
    <clause id="marker_format.id_format">The marker_id MUST be exactly 8 characters long. Each character MUST be a lowercase letter (a-z) or a digit (0-9).</clause>
    <clause id="marker_format.id_generation">The tool MUST generate marker_ids using a cryptographically secure random source. The tool MUST verify that the generated marker_id is not already used by any marker in the workspace. If a collision is detected, the tool MUST regenerate the marker_id.</clause>
    <clause id="marker_format.content_window">The content hash MUST be computed from the N lines immediately after the marker line. N MUST default to 10. N MUST be configurable via a command-line flag. If fewer than N lines remain in the file, the tool MUST hash all remaining lines. If the marker is the last line in the file, the content hash MUST be the hash of an empty string.</clause>
    <clause id="marker_format.content_normalization">Before computing the content hash, each line MUST have trailing whitespace trimmed. Line endings MUST be normalized to \n. Two or more consecutive blank lines MUST be collapsed to a single blank line.</clause>
    <clause id="marker_format.comment_prefix">The tool MUST match the #F directive regardless of the comment character that precedes it. The tool MUST match the directive as a substring, not the comment prefix.</clause>
    <clause id="marker_format.malformed">A line that matches the pattern #F followed by whitespace and id: but does not conform to the well_formed_marker syntax MUST be reported as a malformed_marker.</clause>
  </section>

  <section id="state_file" label="State file">
    <clause id="state_file.location">The filament file MUST be located in the same directory as the spec XML file. The filament file MUST be named .filament.</clause>
    <clause id="state_file.structure">The filament file MUST contain three sections: spec, site, and state. Each section MUST be preceded by a header line in the format [section_name]. Each section MUST contain one or more entries in the format key=value, one per line.</clause>
    <section id="state_file.sections" label="Sections">
      <clause id="state_file.sections.spec">The spec section MUST contain one entry for each clause in the spec. Each entry MUST have the clause id as the key and the spec hash as the value.</clause>
      <clause id="state_file.sections.site">The site section MUST contain one entry for each well_formed_marker found in the workspace. Each entry MUST have the marker_id as the key and the content hash as the value.</clause>
      <clause id="state_file.sections.state">The state section MUST contain one entry for each marker-clause pair. Each entry MUST have the marker_id:clause_id as the key and the reviewed_spec_hash as the value.</clause>
    </section>
    <clause id="state_file.auto_generated">The filament file MUST be auto-generated by the tool. The filament file MUST NOT be edited manually. The filament file MUST include a header comment stating that it is auto-generated and should not be edited.</clause>
  </section>

  <section id="drift" label="Drift model">
    <clause id="drift.spec_drift">A marker exhibits spec_drift when the current spec hash for a clause it references does not match the reviewed_spec_hash stored for that marker-clause pair in the state file. The tool MUST report spec_drift as a finding with the status SPEC_DRIFT.</clause>
    <clause id="drift.site_drift">A marker exhibits site_drift when the current content hash at the marker's site does not match the content hash stored for that marker in the state file. The tool MUST report site_drift as a finding with the status SITE_DRIFT.</clause>
    <clause id="drift.both_drift">When a marker exhibits both spec_drift and site_drift, the tool MUST report two separate findings: one SPEC_DRIFT and one SITE_DRIFT.</clause>
    <clause id="drift.missing">A clause in the spec that has no well_formed_marker in any scanned file MUST be reported as a finding with the status MISSING.</clause>
    <clause id="drift.orphan">A well_formed_marker that references a clause id not in the spec MUST be reported as a finding with the status ORPHAN.</clause>
    <clause id="drift.malformed">A malformed_marker MUST be reported as a finding with the status MALFORMED.</clause>
    <clause id="drift.not_in_state">A well_formed_marker whose marker_id has no entry in the site section of the state file MUST be reported as a finding with the status NOT_IN_STATE.</clause>
    <clause id="drift.state_file_missing">If no .filament file is found in the spec's directory, the tool MUST report a finding with the status STATE_FILE_MISSING.</clause>
    <clause id="drift.duplicate_marker">A well_formed_marker whose marker_id appears in more than one file in the workspace MUST be reported as a finding with the status DUPLICATE_MARKER. The finding MUST include the marker_id, the file path, and the file path where the marker_id was first seen.</clause>
  </section>

  <section id="output" label="Output format">
    <clause id="output.prose">The tool's output MUST be prose. The tool MUST NOT output JSON, logfmt, or any other structured format.</clause>
    <clause id="output.tooltip">The tool MUST print a tooltip preamble at the top of every command's output. The tooltip MUST state that filament tracks whether files stay aligned with their spec, that specs are the source of truth, and that drift means a clause and the content referencing it may have diverged. The tooltip MUST recommend reading the full guide with filament skill. The --quiet flag MUST suppress the tooltip.</clause>
    <clause id="output.finding_prose">For each finding, the tool MUST print prose that includes the status, marker_id (if applicable), clause_id (if applicable), file path (if applicable), line number (if applicable), and an action describing how to resolve the finding. The action MUST include the exact command to run.</clause>
    <clause id="output.result_prose">For each command that modifies the state file, the tool MUST print prose describing what was modified and why the modification matters. The prose MUST include guidance on what to do next.</clause>
    <clause id="output.neutral_language">The tool's output MUST use language that is neutral to the type of file being tracked. The tool MUST NOT assume that tracked files are source code.</clause>
  </section>

  <section id="public_api" label="Public API">
    <clause id="public_api.subcommands">The tool MUST expose the following subcommands: check, status, init, add, resolve, sync, migrate, and skill.</clause>
    <clause id="public_api.check">The check subcommand MUST take zero or more file or directory paths. The tool MUST validate the spec against all parser rules. The tool MUST load the state file. The tool MUST scan the given paths for well_formed_marker elements. The tool MUST detect every spec_drift, site_drift, missing, orphan, malformed_marker, not_in_state, and state_file_missing condition. The tool MUST print every finding to standard error as prose. The tool MUST exit 1 if any finding is found, 0 otherwise.</clause>
    <clause id="public_api.status">The status subcommand MUST take zero or more file or directory paths. The tool MUST display every marker and its drift state. The tool MUST always exit 0, regardless of whether any findings are found.</clause>
    <clause id="public_api.init">The init subcommand MUST take zero or more file or directory paths. The tool MUST compute all spec hashes from the current spec. The tool MUST scan the given paths for well_formed_marker elements. The tool MUST compute content hashes for each marker. The tool MUST create the state file with the spec section, site section, and state section populated. The tool MUST exit 0.</clause>
    <clause id="public_api.add">The add subcommand MUST take one or more clause ids. For each clause id, the tool MUST verify that it is a defined id in the spec. If any clause id is not defined, the tool MUST print an error message and exit 1. If all clause ids are defined, the tool MUST generate a new marker_id and print a well_formed_marker line to standard output. The tool MUST exit 0.</clause>
    <clause id="public_api.resolve">The resolve subcommand MUST accept a scope flag: --spec or --site. The resolve subcommand MUST accept one or more marker_ids. If --spec is specified, the tool MUST update the state section for each marker-clause pair by setting the reviewed_spec_hash to the current spec hash for that clause. If --site is specified, the tool MUST update the site section for each marker by setting the content hash to the current content hash at the marker's site. If --site is specified and the marker has no entry in the state section for any clause it references, the tool MUST create the missing state section entries by setting the reviewed_spec_hash to the current spec hash for each clause. The tool MUST exit 0.</clause>
    <clause id="public_api.sync">The sync subcommand MUST recompute the spec section of the state file from the current spec. The sync subcommand MUST NOT modify the site section or state section. The tool MUST exit 0.</clause>
    <clause id="public_api.migrate">The migrate subcommand MUST take zero or more file or directory paths. The tool MUST scan the given paths for lines containing the old filament:hash directive. For each group of adjacent lines in the same file, the tool MUST generate a new marker_id, rewrite the lines as a single well_formed_marker line, and create the state file with all three sections populated. The tool MUST exit 0.</clause>
    <clause id="public_api.skill">The skill subcommand MUST print a comprehensive usage guide to standard output. The guide MUST cover the marker format, the state file structure, the drift model, the command usage, and the spec-first philosophy. The guide MUST be self-contained and not require external files. The tool MUST exit 0.</clause>
    <clause id="public_api.file_walk">File and directory arguments MUST be walked recursively. Non-text files MUST be skipped silently. If no file or directory arguments are given, the tool MUST default to the current directory.</clause>
  </section>

  <section id="self_hosting" label="Self-hosting">
    <clause id="self_hosting.test">The tool's test suite MUST include a test that runs filament check against the filament.spec.xml file, a .filament state file, and a fixture source file containing a well_formed_marker for each of the tool.name, public_api.subcommands, and path_format.structure clauses, and expects exit 0.</clause>
  </section>

  <section id="versioning" label="Versioning">
    <clause id="versioning.source">This specification is versioned by the git commit that introduces it.</clause>
    <clause id="versioning.amendments">Amendments follow the project's standard pull-request process.</clause>
  </section>

  <section id="parser_rules" label="Parser rules">
    <clause id="parser_rules.description_ignored">A description element, if present, MUST appear at most once and only at the top level. Its content is human-readable documentation and MUST NOT contribute to spec data or hashes.</clause>
    <clause id="parser_rules.path_group">The id of a clause or section that is a child of a section MUST equal the child_id of the section's id.</clause>
    <clause id="parser_rules.no_forward_refs">A clause or term MUST cite only ids that have been defined earlier in the spec.</clause>
    <clause id="parser_rules.no_cycles">The reference graph MUST be acyclic.</clause>
    <clause id="parser_rules.no_self_references">A clause or term MUST NOT cite its own id.</clause>
    <clause id="parser_rules.no_text_on_sections">A section element MUST NOT contain non-whitespace text content.</clause>
    <clause id="parser_rules.no_empty_clauses">A clause element MUST contain non-whitespace text content.</clause>
    <clause id="parser_rules.no_empty_sections">A section element MUST contain at least one sub-clause or sub-section.</clause>
    <clause id="parser_rules.no_empty_terms">A term element MUST contain non-whitespace text content.</clause>
    <clause id="parser_rules.unique_ids">Each clause id, section id, and term text MUST be unique within the spec.</clause>
    <clause id="parser_rules.valid_id_format">A clause id, section id, and term text MUST match [a-z0-9_]+ per segment.</clause>
    <clause id="parser_rules.single_definitions">A spec MUST contain at most one definitions block.</clause>
    <clause id="parser_rules.terms_in_definitions">A term element MUST appear only inside a definitions block.</clause>
  </section>

</spec>
