<module name="orch">
<spec id="init">Init creates an empty .drift/state.xml file by saving an empty State.</spec>
<spec id="todo">Todo loads State, scans the filesystem, reconciles specs and markers, builds a CoreAlgorithmContext with TodoAction, runs the core algorithm, and returns the EvaluatedState without saving.</spec>
<spec id="reset">Reset loads State, scans the filesystem, reconciles specs and markers, builds a CoreAlgorithmContext with ResetAction targeting the given marker and spec, runs the core algorithm, and saves the resulting State to disk. It also writes baseline files for the resolved spec and marker using their current scanned content. When specID is empty (single-arg mode), calls ResetOrphan instead.</spec>
<spec id="link">Link loads State, scans the filesystem, reconciles, validates that the marker and spec exist, rejects duplicate links, saves the State with the new link appended, and writes baseline files for the spec and marker using their current scanned content (content-addressed by hash, dedup-safe).</spec>
<spec id="unlink">Unlink loads State, finds the link matching the given marker and spec, removes it from Links, also removes any ResolutionState entries for that edge, and saves the State. If no matching link exists, returns an error.</spec>
<spec id="reconcile_specs">ReconcileSpecs compares baselined specs against scanned specs. Baselined specs not found on disk are kept in the result with Deleted=true and their baseline hash preserved (no error). New specs in the scan get baseline equal to current hash. Existing specs keep their baselined baseline hash but update filepath and line number.</spec>
<spec id="reconcile_markers">ReconcileMarkers compares baselined markers against scanned markers. Baselined markers not found on disk are kept in the result with Deleted=true and their baseline hash preserved (no error). New markers in the scan get baseline equal to current hash. Existing markers keep their baselined baseline hash but update filepath and line number.</spec>
<spec id="orphan_reset">ResetOrphan takes a single ID. If the ID contains a dot, it is treated as a spec ID; otherwise as a marker ID. If the entry is stale (not on disk, no links), it is removed from state.xml along with any resolutions. If still on disk, errors. If it has links, errors with guidance to resolve them first.</spec>
<spec id="diff">Diff loads State, scans the filesystem, reconciles specs and markers, and returns a DiffResult with both spec and marker sides. Each side contains: ID, filepath, line range (markers only), baseline hash (from state.xml), current hash (from scan), baseline content (from BaselineStore), current content (read from disk), HasBaseline flag (false if no snapshot), and Deleted flag (true if entity removed from disk). Read-only — does not modify state.</spec>
</module>
