<module name="cli">
<spec id="dispatch">Run dispatches on args[0] to init, todo, reset, link, unlink, list, show, help, or skill. No args, --help, -h, and help all print the help text with exit code 0. Unknown commands return an error message with help text and exit code 1. Missing args for reset/link/unlink/show return a usage message with an example and exit code 1. For link, reset, unlink, and show, if args[1] is --help or -h, print command-specific usage with exit code 0. Reset accepts 1 arg (orphan cleanup) or 2 args (edge resolution).</spec>
<spec id="help">The help command prints a multi-line reference: tool description, a prominent "First time? Run drift skill" suggestion, all commands with syntax (including show), marker syntax (range-start/range-end pairs), spec file format (main or module root, spec as direct child, module.spec qualification), quick start, and worked examples. Exit code 0.</spec>
<spec id="skill">The skill command prints a comprehensive embedded guide covering: what driftpin is, the full workflow (init, specs, markers with range-start/range-end, link, todo, reset, show), spec file format with module/import system, marker syntax and range hashing model, CLI command table (including show and list --verbose), drift detection model, drift.pin and drift.ignore files, and an edge cases section (unpaired markers, nested ranges, deleted specs/markers, orphan cleanup, reset semantics, todo exit codes). Exit code 0.</spec>
<spec id="init_template">The init command creates drift.pin (empty state), and if main.pin.xml does not already exist, writes a starter template with a single example spec. The output message instructs the user to edit main.pin.xml, place markers, and run drift skill.</spec>
<spec id="format_todo">formatTodo distinguishes empty vs clean: if no specs and no markers exist, it returns "Nothing to check: no specs or markers registered." with guidance. If synced, it returns "No changes detected. N specs, M markers, K links in sync." Otherwise it prints counts of changed markers and specs, then lists each todo with edge description, file locations, drift reason (including deletion-specific message when a spec or marker has been deleted), and the reset command to run. The todo command exits 0 when clean, 1 when drift exists, 2 on error.</spec>
<spec id="reset_format">The reset command accepts either one or two arguments. With two arguments (marker and module.spec), it resolves a drifted edge. With one argument (an ID containing a dot for specs, no dot for markers), it removes an orphaned deleted entry from drift.pin. Missing arguments return a usage error showing both forms. On success with two args, returns "Resolved: MARKER → SPEC. Baseline updated." with exit code 0. On success with one arg, returns "Removed deleted spec/marker X from drift.pin" with exit code 0. On error returns the error message with exit code 1.</spec>
<spec id="link_format">The link command requires a marker and a module.spec argument, space-separated. Missing arguments return a usage error with an example. On success it returns "Linked marker X to spec Y" with exit code 0. On error it returns a prescriptive error message with exit code 1.</spec>
<spec id="unlink_format">The unlink command requires a marker and a module.spec argument, space-separated. Missing arguments return a usage error with an example. On success it returns "Unlinked marker X from spec Y" with exit code 0. On error it returns the error message with exit code 1.</spec>
<spec id="list_format">The list command shows all specs, markers, links, and sync state. If no specs and no markers exist, it returns "No specs or markers registered." with guidance. Otherwise it prints specs sorted by ID with filepath (no line number for specs) and [deleted] or [unlinked] tags, markers sorted by ID with filepath:startline-endline and [deleted] or [unlinked] tags, and links with marker to spec and [synced] or [DRIFTED] status. The --verbose flag adds spec text (truncated to 80 chars) and the first line of marker range content.</spec>
<spec id="reset_orphan">When reset is called with a single ID argument, the CLI dispatches to ResetOrphan. If the ID contains a dot, it is treated as a spec ID; otherwise as a marker ID. On success, prints "Removed deleted spec/marker X from drift.pin" with exit code 0.</spec>
<spec id="prescriptive_link_errors">When link fails because the marker is unknown, the error message explains that markers must be D! id=shortcode comment lines and lists all available markers. When link fails because the spec is unknown, the error message explains that spec IDs are module-qualified and lists all available specs.</spec>
<spec id="show_command">The show command accepts a single argument: a marker ID (no dot) or spec ID (has dot). It displays the current content of the spec or marker with filepath and line ranges. For a marker ID, it shows any linked specs first, then the marker range content. For a spec ID, it shows the spec text first, then any linked markers range content. Each section is delimited by a === header === line containing the kind, ID, filepath, line range, and hash. If the ID is not found, returns an error with exit code 1.</spec>
</module>
