<module name="cli">
<spec id="dispatch">Run dispatches on args[0] to init, todo, reset, link, unlink, list, show, diff, help, or skill. No args, --help, -h, and help all print the help text with exit code 0. Unknown commands return an error message with help text and exit code 1. Missing args for reset/link/unlink/show/diff return a usage message with an example and exit code 1. Reset accepts 1 arg (orphan cleanup) or 2 args (edge resolution). Diff accepts 1 arg (auto-expand) or 2 args (edge-scoped). Before any subcommand dispatches, two uniform checks run on args[1]: (1) the help_flag check, and (2) the unknown_flag_rejection check. Both run for every subcommand including those that take no arguments (init, todo, skill).</spec>
<spec id="help_flag">For EVERY subcommand (init, todo, list, show, diff, link, unlink, reset, skill), if args[1] is --help or -h, the CLI prints that subcommand's usage text with exit code 0 and does NOT dispatch the subcommand. This check happens uniformly at the top of Run before the switch, so it works for subcommands that take no arguments (init, todo, skill) as well as those that take arguments. Each subcommand's usage text describes its syntax, purpose, and a short example. Top-level `drift` (no args), `drift help`, `drift --help`, and `drift -h` all print the main help text with exit code 0.</spec>
<spec id="unknown_flag_rejection">When any arg to a subcommand starts with `--` and is not a recognized flag for that subcommand, the CLI prints "unknown flag: --XYZ" with exit code 1 and does NOT dispatch the subcommand. This prevents silent misinterpretation where a mistyped or unsupported long flag would be treated as a positional argument (e.g. `drift diff --all` must NOT parse `--all` as a marker ID — it is a recognized flag for diff, see diff_all). Recognized long flags per subcommand: `--help` for all subcommands; `--verbose` for list only; `--all` for diff only. Any other `--foo` is rejected. Short flags follow the same rule: `-h` is recognized for all subcommands; any other `-x` short flag is rejected as "unknown flag: -x". This check runs AFTER the help_flag check, so `--help` is always honored even on subcommands where it is the only recognized flag.</spec>
<spec id="unlinked_warning">When `drift todo` runs and there exist one or more non-deleted markers with no links, the output appends a one-line summary warning after the sync/drift summary. The warning reads "N unlinked marker(s) found — run `drift list` to review." with singular "marker" when N=1 and plural "markers" when N>1. The warning does NOT change the exit code (todo still exits 0 when clean, 1 when drift exists, 2 on error). The warning is suppressed in the "Nothing to check: no specs or markers registered." case (when both specs and markers are empty). Deleted markers (no longer on disk) are not counted as unlinked.</spec>
<spec id="diff_all">The diff command accepts `--all` as its sole flag (in addition to the per-edge and auto-expand forms). `drift diff --all` shows the full unified diff for EVERY drifted edge — every entry currently reported by `drift todo` — concatenated into one output with each edge separated by a `===` divider. This forces the user to review every broken edge before resolving any of them. Synced edges are NOT shown (use `drift list` for the full mapping). When there is no drift, prints "No drift detected." with exit code 0. When drift exists, exit code 0 (diff is read-only; the drift itself is reported by `drift todo`). `--all` is recognized ONLY by diff; no other subcommand accepts it.</spec>
<spec id="no_bulk_reset">DESIGN PRINCIPLE: drift intentionally provides NO command to reset, acknowledge, or dismiss multiple drifted edges at once. `drift reset &lt;marker&gt; &lt;module.spec&gt;` accepts exactly ONE edge per invocation — there is no `--all`, no glob, no multi-arg form, and none will be added. This friction is deliberate and is the whole point of the tool: a bulk reset would let an LLM blindly mark everything as reviewed without actually reviewing the changes, which would make drift useless as a spec-code sync tool. The intended workflow is: `drift todo` (see what broke) → `drift diff --all` (review every broken edge's changes in one pass) → `drift reset &lt;marker&gt; &lt;module.spec&gt;` (resolve ONE edge at a time, after reviewing it). The one-edge-at-a-time reset is the enforcement point: the reset case dispatches to orch.Reset with exactly args[1] (marker) and args[2] (spec) — single strings, never slices.</spec>
<spec id="help">The help command prints a multi-line reference: tool description, a prominent "First time? Run drift skill" suggestion, all commands with syntax (including show and diff), marker syntax (range-start/range-end pairs), spec file format (main or module root, spec as direct child, module.spec qualification), quick start, and worked examples. Exit code 0.</spec>
<spec id="skill">The skill command prints a comprehensive embedded guide covering: what drift is, the full workflow (init, specs, markers with range-start/range-end, link, todo, reset, show, diff including --all), spec file format with module/import system, marker syntax and range hashing model, CLI command table (including show, diff, diff --all, and list --verbose), drift detection model, .drift/ directory layout (state.xml + baselines/), drift.ignore file, a "Why no bulk reset?" section explaining the deliberate friction (no bulk reset exists or will be added; the intended workflow is todo → diff --all → reset one edge at a time), and an edge cases section (unpaired markers, nested ranges, deleted specs/markers, orphan cleanup, reset semantics, todo exit codes). Exit code 0.</spec>
<spec id="init_template">The init command creates .drift/ (containing state.xml and baselines/), and if main.drift.xml does not already exist, writes a starter template with a single example spec. The output message instructs the user to edit main.drift.xml, place markers, and run drift skill. Init is NOT idempotent: if .drift/state.xml already exists (the project is already initialized), init FAILS with an error message instructing the user that the project is already initialized and that re-running init would overwrite existing state. The error mentions the state.xml path and exits with code 1. See init_idempotent for the orchestrator-level enforcement. To forcibly reinitialize, the user must delete .drift/state.xml (or .drift/) by hand — drift provides no command to do this, by design (protecting against accidental state loss).</spec>
<spec id="init_idempotent">The orchestrator's Init() method checks StateStore.Initialized() before writing. If the state store reports already-initialized (state.xml exists on disk), Init() returns ErrAlreadyInitialized without writing. If Initialized() reports false, Init() proceeds to save an empty state (creating state.xml and baselines/). If Initialized() returns a non-not-found error (e.g. malformed state.xml that exists but won't parse), Init() propagates that error rather than silently overwriting — the user must inspect and delete the corrupt state.xml manually. The CLI's init case maps ErrAlreadyInitialized to a user-facing error message with exit code 1.</spec>
<spec id="format_todo">formatTodo distinguishes empty vs clean: if no specs and no markers exist, it returns "Nothing to check: no specs or markers registered." with guidance. If synced, it returns "No changes detected. N specs, M markers, K links in sync." Otherwise it prints counts of changed markers and specs, then lists each todo with edge description, file locations, drift reason (including deletion-specific message when a spec or marker has been deleted), the reset command to run, and a hint line pointing to `drift diff` for seeing what changed. The todo command exits 0 when clean, 1 when drift exists, 2 on error.</spec>
<spec id="reset_format">The reset command accepts either one or two arguments. With two arguments (marker and module.spec), it resolves a drifted edge. With one argument (an ID containing a dot for specs, no dot for markers), it removes an orphaned deleted entry from state.xml. Missing arguments return a usage error showing both forms. On success with two args, returns "Resolved: MARKER → SPEC. Baseline updated." with exit code 0. On success with one arg, returns "Removed deleted spec/marker X from state.xml" with exit code 0. On error returns the error message with exit code 1.</spec>
<spec id="link_format">The link command requires a marker and a module.spec argument, space-separated. Missing arguments return a usage error with an example. On success it returns "Linked marker X to spec Y" with exit code 0. On error it returns a prescriptive error message with exit code 1.</spec>
<spec id="unlink_format">The unlink command requires a marker and a module.spec argument, space-separated. Missing arguments return a usage error with an example. On success it returns "Unlinked marker X from spec Y" with exit code 0. On error it returns the error message with exit code 1.</spec>
<spec id="list_format">The list command shows all specs, markers, links, and sync state. If no specs and no markers exist, it returns "No specs or markers registered." with guidance. Otherwise it prints specs sorted by ID with filepath (no line number for specs) and [deleted] or [unlinked] tags, markers sorted by ID with filepath:startline-endline and [deleted] or [unlinked] tags, and links with marker to spec and [synced] or [DRIFTED] status. The --verbose flag adds spec text (truncated to 80 chars) and the first line of marker range content.</spec>
<spec id="reset_orphan">When reset is called with a single ID argument, the CLI dispatches to ResetOrphan. If the ID contains a dot, it is treated as a spec ID; otherwise as a marker ID. On success, prints "Removed deleted spec/marker X from state.xml" with exit code 0.</spec>
<spec id="prescriptive_link_errors">When link fails because the marker is unknown, the error message explains that markers must be D! id=shortcode comment lines and lists all available markers. When link fails because the spec is unknown, the error message explains that spec IDs are module-qualified and lists all available specs.</spec>
<spec id="show_command">The show command accepts a single argument: a marker ID (no dot) or spec ID (has dot). It displays the current content of the spec or marker with filepath and line ranges. For a marker ID, it shows any linked specs first, then the marker range content. For a spec ID, it shows the spec text first, then any linked markers range content. Each section is delimited by a === header === line containing the kind, ID, filepath, line range, and hash. If the ID is not found, returns an error with exit code 1.</spec>
<spec id="diff_command">The diff command accepts one argument, two arguments, or the `--all` flag. With two arguments (marker and module.spec), it shows a unified diff for that specific edge: spec side and marker side separated by ---. With one argument (a marker ID or spec ID), it auto-expands to all linked edges. With `--all`, see diff_all. Each side shows the entity ID, filepath (and line range for markers), status (in sync / no baseline snapshot / deleted / baseline and current hashes), and if changed, a unified diff of baseline vs current content with --- baseline / +++ current headers. When in sync, prints "Status: in sync" without a diff. When no baseline snapshot exists, prints "Status: no baseline snapshot (hash X)". When deleted, prints "Status: deleted from disk". Exit code 0 on success, 1 on error.</spec>
<spec id="marker_example">The skill guide contains a working example marker (validate_input) in a Go code block demonstrating the range-start/range-end syntax. This marker is drift-tracked — editing the example in skill.md will flag drift, proving that drift can control documentation alongside code.</spec>
</module>
