<module name="cli">
<spec id="dispatch">Run dispatches on args[0] to init, todo, reset, link, unlink, list, show, diff, help, skill, config, or version. No args, --help, -h, and help all print the help text with exit code 0. Unknown commands return an error message with help text and exit code 1. Missing args for reset/link/unlink/show/diff return a usage message with an example and exit code 1. Reset accepts 1 arg (a closure hash) plus optional --dry-run. Diff accepts 1 arg (a closure hash) or `--all`. Link and unlink accept marker+spec args plus optional --dry-run. Before any subcommand dispatches, three uniform checks run: (0) global_flag_stripping removes --json/--no-color/--color= from args (see <ref spec="output.global_flags">global flags</ref>), (1) the help_flag check, and (2) the unknown_flag_rejection check. All run for every subcommand including those that take no arguments (init, todo, skill). The version command flows through dispatch like every other command (see <ref spec="output.version_in_dispatch">version in dispatch</ref>).</spec>
<spec id="help_flag">For EVERY subcommand (init, todo, list, show, diff, link, unlink, reset, skill), if args[1] is --help or -h, the CLI prints that subcommand's usage text with exit code 0 and does NOT dispatch the subcommand. This check happens uniformly at the top of Run before the switch, so it works for subcommands that take no arguments (init, todo, skill) as well as those that take arguments. Each subcommand's usage text describes its syntax, purpose, and a short example. Top-level `drift` (no args), `drift help`, `drift --help`, and `drift -h` all print the main help text with exit code 0.</spec>
<spec id="unknown_flag_rejection">When any arg to a subcommand starts with `--` and is not a recognized flag for that subcommand, the CLI prints "unknown flag: --XYZ" with exit code 1 and does NOT dispatch the subcommand. This prevents silent misinterpretation where a mistyped or unsupported long flag would be treated as a positional argument (e.g. `drift diff --all` must NOT parse `--all` as a hash — it is a recognized flag for diff, see diff_all). Recognized long flags per subcommand: `--help` for all subcommands; `--verbose` for list only; `--all` for diff only; `--dry-run` for reset, link, and unlink only. Any other `--foo` is rejected. Short flags follow the same rule: `-h` is recognized for all subcommands; any other `-x` short flag is rejected as "unknown flag: -x". This check runs AFTER the help_flag check, so `--help` is always honored even on subcommands where it is the only recognized flag. NOTE: The global flags --json, --no-color, and --color= are stripped by the global_flag_stripping pre-pass BEFORE this check runs, so they never trigger unknown_flag_rejection. See <ref spec="output.global_flag_stripping">global flag stripping</ref> and principles.specs_are_truth.</spec>
<spec id="unlinked_warning">When `drift todo` runs and there exist one or more non-deleted markers with no links, the output appends a one-line summary warning after the closure list. The warning reads "N unlinked marker(s) found — run `drift list` to review." with singular "marker" when N=1 and plural "markers" when N>1. Unlinked markers are treated as actionable drift: todo exits 1 when unlinked markers exist, even if no closures are derived (exit 0 means all specs are linked AND no closures exist). This makes `drift todo` safe as a CI gate — unlinked markers represent unfinished coverage work. The warning is suppressed in the "Nothing to check: no specs or markers registered." case (when both specs and markers are empty). Deleted markers (no longer on disk) are not counted as unlinked. See principles.friction.</spec>
<spec id="diff_all">The diff command accepts `--all` as its sole flag (in addition to the per-closure form). `drift diff --all` shows the full unified diff for EVERY closure — every closure currently reported by `drift todo` — concatenated into one output with each closure separated by an `=== Closure HASH ===` divider. This forces the user to review every drift event before resolving any of them. Synced nodes are NOT shown (use `drift list` for the full mapping). When there is no drift, prints "No drift detected." with exit code 0. When drift exists, exit code 0 (diff is read-only; the drift itself is reported by `drift todo`). `--all` is recognized ONLY by diff; no other subcommand accepts it. See principles.friction.</spec>
<spec id="no_bulk_reset">DESIGN PRINCIPLE: drift intentionally provides NO command to reset, acknowledge, or dismiss multiple closures at once. `drift reset &lt;hash&gt;` accepts exactly ONE closure per invocation — there is no `--all`, no glob, no multi-arg form, and none will be added. This friction is deliberate and is the whole point of the tool: a bulk reset would let an LLM blindly mark everything as reviewed without actually reviewing the changes, which would make drift useless as a spec-code sync tool. The intended workflow is: `drift todo` (see which closures drifted) → `drift diff --all` (review every closure's changes in one pass) → `drift reset &lt;hash&gt;` (resolve ONE closure at a time, after reviewing it). The one-closure-at-a-time reset is the enforcement point: the reset case dispatches to orch.ResetClosure with exactly args[1] (hash) — a single string, never a slice. See principles.friction.</spec>
<spec id="help">The help command prints a multi-line reference: tool description, a prominent "First time? Run drift skill" suggestion, all commands with syntax (including show, diff, config theme, and version), global flags (--json, --no-color, --color), available themes, marker syntax (range-start/range-end pairs), spec file format (main or module root, spec as direct child, module.spec qualification), quick start, and worked examples. Exit code 0.</spec>
<spec id="skill">The skill command prints a comprehensive embedded guide covering: what drift is, the full workflow (init, specs, markers with range-start/range-end, link, todo, reset, show, diff including --all), spec file format with module/import system, marker syntax and range hashing model, CLI command table (including show, diff, diff --all, list --verbose, config theme, and version), output modes (Plain, Color, JSON with --json flag for LLM consumption), theming system (12 built-in themes, drift config theme command, .drift/theme.xml custom project theme, .drift/user-settings.xml per-user preference), closure-driven drift detection model, .drift/ directory layout (state.xml, baselines.bin, theme.xml, user-settings.xml, .gitignore), drift.ignore file, a "Why no bulk reset?" section explaining the deliberate friction (no bulk reset exists or will be added; the intended workflow is todo → diff → reset one closure at a time), a "Decision tree" section giving explicit guidance for resolving each drift event kind (NODE_CHANGED on marker vs. spec; NODE_ADDED; NODE_REMOVED; EDGE_ADDED; EDGE_REMOVED; EDGE_BROKEN — see cli.skill_decision_tree), a "Marker placement" section guiding marker placement during refactors (keep the marker on the public entry-point function; helpers stay outside the marked range unless they warrant their own marker + spec; nested markers are supported but produce noisier diffs; see cli.skill_marker_placement), and an edge cases section (unpaired markers, nested ranges, deleted specs/markers, broken-edge persistence, reset semantics, todo exit codes). Exit code 0. See principles.friction and principles.self_hosting.</spec>
<spec id="init_template">The init command creates .drift/ (containing state.xml), and if main.drift.xml does not already exist, writes a starter template with a single example spec. It also creates .drift/.gitignore containing "user-settings.xml" and "state.lock" to prevent accidental commits of per-user theme preferences and runtime lock files. The output message instructs the user to edit main.drift.xml, place markers, and run drift skill. Init is idempotent at the CLI level: if .drift/state.xml already exists (the project is already initialized), init prints "Already initialized. Run `drift todo` to check state." with exit code 0 and does NOT modify any existing files. To forcibly reinitialize, the user must delete .drift/state.xml (or .drift/) by hand — drift provides no command to do this, by design (protecting against accidental state loss). See init_idempotent for the orchestrator-level enforcement. Note: baselines.bin is created lazily on the first baseline write (e.g. drift link), not by init itself.</spec>
<spec id="init_idempotent">The orchestrator's Init(sess) method takes a fileio.Session and checks StateStore.Initialized() before writing. If the state store reports already-initialized (state.xml exists on disk), Init() returns ErrAlreadyInitialized without writing. If Initialized() reports false, Init() proceeds to save an empty state via the Session (creating state.xml). If Initialized() returns a non-not-found error (e.g. malformed state.xml that exists but won't parse), Init() propagates that error rather than silently overwriting — the user must inspect and delete the corrupt state.xml manually. The CLI's init case maps ErrAlreadyInitialized to a friendly "Already initialized" message with exit code 0 (not an error). See principles.specs_are_truth.</spec>
<spec id="format_todo">formatClosure distinguishes empty vs clean: if no specs and no markers exist, it returns "Nothing to check: no specs or markers registered." with guidance. If synced, it returns "No changes detected. N specs, M markers, K edges in sync." Otherwise it prints "N closure(s) with drift." then per-closure blocks: the 8-character hash, member counts (specs/markers/edges), an Events section (NODE-CHANGED/NODE-ADDED/NODE-REMOVED/EDGE-ADDED/EDGE-REMOVED/BROKEN-EDGE with appropriate detail), a Members section (specs and markers listed), and the inspect/resolve commands using the hash. The todo command exits 0 when clean (all linked + no closures), 1 when closures exist or unlinked markers are present, 2 on error. See principles.friction and unlinked_warning.</spec>
<spec id="reset_format">The reset command requires exactly one argument: an 8-character closure hash, plus an optional --dry-run flag. Missing arguments return a usage error with an example. Without --dry-run: on success it prints "Closure HASH resolved." followed by a per-event change summary (each node hash delta truncated to 8 chars, each edge add/remove) and exits 0. With --dry-run: it prints the same change summary prefixed by a "Preview — no changes written" line and exits 3 (special code alerting LLM consumers that no state mutation occurred). Closures containing only broken-edge events are refused with an error directing the user to fix the scan. Unknown hashes return a "closure hash not found; run `drift todo` to list current closures" error. See principles.friction.</spec>
<spec id="link_format">The link command requires a marker and a module.spec argument, space-separated, plus an optional --dry-run flag. Missing arguments return a usage error with an example. Without --dry-run: on success it prints "Linked marker X to spec Y" followed by a one-line change summary (the edge that will be added) and exits 0. With --dry-run: it prints the same summary prefixed by a "Preview — no changes written" line and exits 3. On error (unknown marker/spec, duplicate edge) it returns a prescriptive error message with exit code 1.</spec>
<spec id="unlink_format">The unlink command requires a marker and a module.spec argument, space-separated, plus an optional --dry-run flag. Missing arguments return a usage error with an example. Without --dry-run: on success it prints "Unlinked marker X from spec Y" followed by a one-line change summary (the edge that will be removed) and exits 0. With --dry-run: it prints the same summary prefixed by a "Preview — no changes written" line and exits 3. On error (no matching edge) it returns the error message with exit code 1.</spec>
<spec id="list_format">The list command shows all specs, markers, edges, and sync state. If no specs and no markers exist, it returns "No specs or markers registered." with guidance. Otherwise it prints specs sorted by ID with filepath (no line number for specs) and [deleted], [unlinked], or [DRIFTED] tags, markers sorted by ID with filepath:startline-endline and the same tags, and edges sorted lexicographically by (From, To) with From → To and [synced] or [DRIFTED] status. The edge sort makes `drift list` output diff-stable across runs (state-store mutations may otherwise shuffle the slice). The --verbose flag adds spec text (truncated to 80 chars) and the first line of marker range content.</spec>
<spec id="prescriptive_link_errors">When link fails because the marker is unknown, the error message explains that markers must be D! id=shortcode comment lines and lists all available markers. When link fails because the spec is unknown, the error message explains that spec IDs are module-qualified and lists all available specs. See principles.specs_are_truth.</spec>
<spec id="show_command">The show command accepts a single argument: a marker ID (no dot) or spec ID (has dot). It displays the current content of the spec or marker with filepath and line ranges. For a marker ID, it shows any linked specs first, then the marker range content. For a spec ID, it shows the spec text first, then any linked markers range content. Each section is delimited by a === header === line containing the kind, ID, filepath, line range, and hash. If the ID is not found, returns an error with exit code 1. See principles.friction — review before resolve.</spec>
<spec id="diff_command">The diff command accepts one argument (a closure hash) or the `--all` flag. With a hash, it shows unified diffs for every node in the closure: spec sides and marker sides separated by ---. With `--all`, see diff_all. Each side shows the entity ID annotated with its role in the closure — [SEED] for the node that originated the closure (matches one of the closure's event Seed fields) or [citer] for a transitively-reached citer — followed by filepath (and line range for markers), status (in sync / no baseline snapshot / deleted / baseline and current hashes), and if changed, a unified diff of baseline vs current content with --- baseline / +++ current headers. When in sync, prints "Status: in sync" without a diff. When no baseline snapshot exists, prints "Status: no baseline snapshot (hash X)". When deleted, prints "Status: deleted from disk". Exit code 0 on success, 1 on error. See principles.friction — review before resolve.</spec>
<spec id="marker_example">The skill guide contains a working example marker (auth_login) in a Go code block demonstrating the range-start/range-end syntax. This marker is drift-tracked — editing the example in skill.md will flag drift, proving that drift can control documentation alongside code. See principles.self_hosting.</spec>
<spec id="skill_decision_tree">The skill guide includes a "Decision tree" section that gives explicit guidance for resolving each drift event kind in a closure. The tree is a table with at least these columns: Event kind | Question to ask | If yes | If no. It covers every drift event kind (NODE_CHANGED on marker, NODE_CHANGED on spec, NODE_ADDED, NODE_REMOVED, EDGE_ADDED, EDGE_REMOVED, EDGE_BROKEN). Drift itself is a deterministic signal — it reports that a hash changed but does not judge whether the change is semantically consistent with the spec. The decision tree is the rubric the reviewer (human or LLM) applies to decide whether to update code, update the spec, or fix a citation before resetting the closure.</spec>
<spec id="skill_marker_placement">The skill guide includes a "Marker placement" section that gives guidance for marker placement during refactors and routine edits. Conventions: keep the marker on the public entry-point function that the spec describes; helpers stay outside the marked range unless they warrant their own spec + marker; nested markers are supported but produce noisier diffs and are not preferred. Drift is content-addressed — a marker reports changes to the bytes inside its range. Refactors that move code across a marker boundary without changing behavior still produce NODE_CHANGED events (intentional); the reviewer's job is to confirm the move didn't change semantics. There is no "this was just a refactor" annotation; the reviewer must judge.</spec>
<spec id="config_command">The config command provides a namespace for user-specific preferences. Currently supports one subcommand: `drift config theme NAME` which writes the theme preference to .drift/user-settings.xml (not committed to git; .drift/.gitignore is created by drift init to exclude it). `drift config theme` with no NAME argument prints the current effective theme. Unknown theme names are rejected with an error listing the 12 available themes. Missing the subcommand (e.g. bare `drift config`) returns a usage error. See <ref spec="output.config_theme">config theme</ref> and <ref spec="output_impl.user_settings">user settings</ref>.</spec>
</module>
