<module name="core">
<spec id="validate">Validate must reject duplicate spec IDs, duplicate marker IDs, duplicate links, links referencing unknown specs or markers, resolution entries referencing unknown specs, unknown markers, unlinked edges, or duplicate resolution entries. Validation must pass when all references are consistent.</spec>
<spec id="todo_action">Given a TodoAction with a Scan covering all spec and marker IDs, the algorithm must produce a todo per linked edge where the current hash differs from the baseline and no resolution entry matches the current hashes. Edges where both sides are unchanged must produce no todo. Edges with a matching resolution entry must produce no todo. When a spec or marker has been deleted (scan hash is empty string), the todo must set the corresponding Deleted flag.</spec>
<spec id="reset_action">Given a ResetAction targeting a linked edge, the algorithm must record a resolution entry with the current spec and marker hashes, then collapse all nodes whose every edge is either consistent or has a matching resolution entry. Collapse updates the baseline hash to the current scan hash and prunes resolution entries for collapsed edges. When a node's scan hash is empty string (deleted), collapse removes the node entirely and filters out its links. The target edge must be in links or the action errors.</spec>
<spec id="collapse">Collapse runs iteratively. In each pass, any marker whose every edge is checked gets its baseline hash updated to the current scan hash. Same for specs. When a node's scan hash is empty string (deleted), the node is removed from the result and its links are filtered out. Passes repeat until no node collapses. After all passes complete, resolution entries for collapsed nodes are pruned: deleted nodes get all resolutions pruned unconditionally, non-deleted collapsed nodes get resolutions pruned when the other side is in sync. This enables progressive collapse across many-to-many topologies.</spec>
<spec id="edge_unchecked">An edge is unchecked when the current marker hash or current spec hash differs from the baseline and no resolution entry records the current hashes. If both baseline hashes match the current scan hashes, the edge is consistent and not unchecked. If a resolution entry exists with matching current hashes, the edge is not unchecked. Nil markers or specs (already pruned) are treated as having an empty baseline hash.</spec>
<spec id="scan_coverage">The scan must provide a hash for every spec and marker in the context, including empty string for deleted entries. Missing hashes for known specs or markers cause an error. Unknown spec or marker hashes in the scan that are not in the context also cause an error.</spec>
<spec id="deleted_drift">When a spec or marker is deleted from disk but still in .drift/state.xml, the reconciler keeps it with a sentinel empty-string scan hash. This triggers drift on all linked edges. The Todo struct records SpecDeleted or MarkerDeleted. After reset, collapse prunes the deleted node and its links from the result.</spec>
</module>
