<module name="testutil">
<spec id="constructors">
Overview: Constructor helpers for core types used across drift's test suite. Each returns a fully-populated Spec, Marker, or Edge with sensible default Filepath/LineNumber fields so tests can specify only the semantically relevant fields.

Defined terms:
  Spec    — see glossary.spec; constructed with ID + Hash
  Marker  — see glossary.marker; constructed with ID + Hash
  Edge    — see glossary.edge; constructed with From + To

Requirements:
  R1. NewSpec(id, hash) MUST return a Spec with Filepath = id + ".xml" and LineNumber = 10. The LineNumber is a stable placeholder so tests don't depend on real file layouts.
  R2. NewSpecWithLocation(id, hash, filepath, lineNumber) MUST return a Spec with the caller-supplied Filepath and LineNumber verbatim.
  R3. NewMarker(id, hash) MUST return a Marker with Filepath = id + ".go", LineNumber = 20, EndLineNumber = 30. The 10-line span is a stable placeholder.
  R4. NewMarkerWithLocation(id, hash, filepath, lineNumber) MUST return a Marker with EndLineNumber = lineNumber + 10. The 10-line span is the convention.
  R5. NewLink(specID, markerID) MUST return an Edge with From = markerID and To = specID. The argument order (spec first, marker second) is preserved from the pre-collapse API for test readability; reviewers MUST read carefully.
  R6. NewRef(fromSpec, toSpec) MUST return an Edge with From = fromSpec and To = toSpec. Argument order matches the citation direction (citer first, cited second).

See also: glossary.spec, glossary.marker, glossary.edge.
</spec>

<spec id="assertions">
Overview: Test assertion helpers that call t.Helper() so failure reports point to the caller, not the helper. Each compares one structural property of drift's state types and fatals on mismatch with a descriptive message.

Requirements:
  R1. AssertNoError(t, err) MUST fatal when err != nil with the error in the message.
  R2. AssertErrorWraps(t, err, target) MUST fatal when errors.Is(err, target) returns false.
  R3. AssertClosureCount(t, state, want) MUST fatal when len(state.Closures) != want.
  R4. AssertBaselineHashes(t, state, specID, wantSpecHash, markerID, wantMarkerHash) MUST fatal when either the named spec or the named marker in state has a hash different from its want value.
  R5. AssertStateEquals(t, got, want) MUST fatal when got and want differ in Specs, Markers, or Edges (compared as deep-equal after normalizing slice order).
  R6. AssertNodeInClosure / AssertNodeNotInClosure MUST scan the closure's Nodes for the given ID and fatal according to presence.
  R7. Every assertion helper MUST call t.Helper() so the failure line points to the test, not the helper.

See also: glossary.closure.
</spec>

<spec id="fixtures">
Overview: File-writing helpers for test setup: WriteSpecFile, WriteCodeFile, WriteIgnoreFile create real files in t.TempDir() so scanner/orchestrator tests exercise the real I/O path rather than mocks.

Requirements:
  R1. WriteSpecFile(t, dir, name, content) MUST write dir/name with the given content and 0644 permissions. The directory MUST exist before the call.
  R2. WriteCodeFile(t, dir, name, content) MUST write dir/name with the given content and 0644 permissions.
  R3. WriteIgnoreFile(t, dir, content) MUST write dir/drift.ignore with the given content and 0644 permissions. The filename is fixed (drift.ignore is the canonical ignore filename).
  R4. All three helpers MUST fatal via t.Fatalf on any write error; they do not return an error to the caller.

See also: scanner.text_file_detection.
</spec>

<spec id="finders">
Overview: Lookup helpers that scan slices of Spec, Marker, Closure, or EvaluatedState for a specific entity by ID or hash. Used when a test needs to inspect a particular result without assuming slice order.

Requirements:
  R1. FindScanResultSpec / FindScanResultMarker MUST return the matching Spec/Marker and true, or the zero value and false if not found.
  R2. FindSpecInEvaluatedState / FindMarkerInEvaluatedState MUST fatal via t.Fatalf if the entity is not found. Tests using these helpers assume presence; absence is a test bug.
  R3. FindClosureByHash MUST fatal if no closure has the given hash.
  R4. FindClosureContainingNode MUST fatal if no closure contains the given node ID.
  R5. EvaluatedToState MUST convert EvaluatedState to statestore.State by dropping Closures and Scan, preserving Specs/Markers/Edges. Used when a test wants to feed evaluated output back into a stateStore.

See also: glossary.closure.
</spec>

<spec id="sha1_helper">
Overview: ExpectedSha1Hex(content) returns the sha1 hex digest of content. Used in tests to compute the expected canonical hash for a given input without duplicating the algorithm.

Requirements:
  R1. ExpectedSha1Hex MUST return the same hex string that crypto/sha1 would produce for the same input, formatted with %x.
  R2. ExpectedSha1Hex MUST NOT strip refs or normalize content — it operates on the raw input bytes. (Spec canonical hashing strips refs; this helper does not, because tests usually want the marker-content hash, not the spec canonical hash.)

See also: scanner.hash_sha1.
</spec>
</module>
